Oh Vasu Deva suitum deivam come such aa
Dunham's Devaki paramanandam krishna
monday jagadguru let's chant sixteen
onwards we have done 16 17 18
today's 19 let's just just follow me in
the chanting chant of to me now so to
videotape abu nasr to V dirty Bravo
Navid dirty with dirty repeat reached
wanted restaurant aha
vana use that to Adarsh if he to an iota
- ah - Evie Avinashi tooted with the
Avinashi tooted with dy7 me Tom Tom yena
sarvam idam tatam we know some of us yes
we know some of us
nikasha it car - maratti Nahas chitkul -
morality under bond a medium and a made
me tea soup Tasha Irina
Natasha Irina an ocean Oprah me yes
machine Oprah me yes the smart you just
swap out
the smart you're desperate in response
to a practical question by Arjuna Arjuna
simply asked what he should do what's
right and what's wrong but Krishna goes
very deep he starts with the very nature
of the self the root of all wisdom
before deciding what is right and wrong
what you should do and should not do
first you should know what you are and
so here he teaches the most profound
doctrine of the self of what we really
are maybe this is the central teaching
the first teaching of Advaita Vedanta of
course the bhagavad-gita has many more
things to say but this is this is the
key so Krishna starts with that he tells
us with what we think ourselves to be
that we are not he makes a distinction
between the body and the embodied self
sharira sharira sharira means body and
we're body we do not just mean the
physical body when we look at ourselves
we find two aspects one is the physical
body this one what everybody can see
what the doctor checks up and what what
you have inside what you inside only me
I mean how do you say it because inside
the physical body is only more physical
body inside closer to your psychic being
your your inner being your thoughts your
ideas your memories the person that you
think you are even that is a body even
that is not what you are so the physical
body outside by outside I mean relative
to the inner self the physical body
outside and the inner psychological body
the gross bodies to lasheeda and the
subtle body suksham sharir both our
bodies we are not then that's what
krishna says and the first so we are the
Atman the self Atman literally means the
self
you and this body and mind what we
considered to be ourselves are an art
man not self what is the characteristic
of the self as distinguished from the
not self how is it different what are we
talking about here well first of all
Trishna says it does not die he starts
up we will see that very 12th verse in
fact from verses 11 to 25 is a central
teaching of the deduction of the self
Atman from 11 to 25 second chapter 12
verse he says there was never a time
when you were not or I was not not these
Kings were not and they will never be a
time when we will not be he does not say
that we are here right now because
that's obvious we are here right now but
did we exist before our birth are we
going to exist after the death of this
body he says yes what's going to exist
not the body the body is the not-self
the not-self will die the mind is the
not-self
it will change but there is an
unchanging reality which is you the real
you that does not die with the death of
the body that does not change or forget
with changing and forgetting mind so
that one we are first of all it is nitya
eternal what is nectar eternal the self
you are eternal in the 13th
it showed how the body goes through
childhood youth middle age old age and
these transitions you say that you are
the one who was the kid you are the one
who was the teenager you are the one who
was the middle-aged person you are the
one who are who is you call yourself a
senior person now but it's the body
which best made these transitions as you
claim without any doubt whatsoever that
you persisted through these changes of
the body so also the claim here is you
will persist through the final change of
the body which is death so that was the
13th verse the sixteenth verse is very
important it tells us something one more
thing about the
self about you about the Atman it says
the Atman is real and the not self an
Atman is false and appearance what did
the what's the first thing it said the
Atman is eternal and the not self is non
eternal changing dying the second thing
it says not only is the not self world
body and mind non eternal but also it's
an appearance it's not real in itself
what is real in itself you the self I
will not go into explanation I hope you
remember we did a full class on this
16th verse very important not only is
the body-mind non eternal but the body
mind is also is an appearance in what in
the self what is the self pure being not
only pure awareness but pure being is
this do you remember the isness never
gota goes out of existence and that
which appears never truly exists we
discussed the concepts of borrowed
existence and intrinsic existence all
those things we discussed do you
remember the example of the potato which
was hot and the water and the fire
underneath so that is given in that
sixteenth verse very important verse it
tells you Atma satyam jagat mithya it
takes a lifetime to digest this it's a
stunning revelation and a message of
hope if there is anything real in the
world if there is anything real in this
life it is you but not in a solipsistic
sense by solipsistic since I mean I
alone am real and you are all false know
the real I and the real you are one and
the same thing your reality is the
reality of the entire universe that
means there's the core of reality which
you are and that lense reality - what we
call the universe
body mind and life then he goes on 1820
in verse another beautiful one he makes
another point about the self he says the
self is all-pervading look at how he is
hitting our fondest conceptions of
ourselves first conception is I'm going
to die
this is not you are immortal second
conception is here is a real stark
reality no you are the reality that is a
dependent reality depends on you for the
reality third we think I am here and
everything else is outside and separate
from everything he says no you pervade
the entirety of of reality
how how is it that I pervade everything
it's only when you are localized in the
body that I think I am this one then you
feel and I am here and not there but we
suppose you identify yourself with
easeness existence where are you not if
you are not there that thing will become
he's not not it'll disappear if isness
is not there it'll become is not you
pervade everything as pure being or more
precisely everything has its dwelling in
you because you are pure being you
pervade all experiences of life as pure
consciousness because without that
consciousness no experience is possible
so as pure being as pure awareness you
pervade everything there's nothing that
can be there without you and I know I'm
rushing through but I'm giving you the
highlights of what has happened so you
are all pervasive then the eighteenth
verse many things was many ways said one
word was a premiere very important
another interesting point he makes on
everything that we know in this world is
an object of knowledge by definition if
you know it it's an object of knowledge
what you see is an object of seeing what
you hear is an object of hearing smell
taste touch or belief an object of
believing the read in books religious
books and we're taught to believe in
heaven hell God or object of scientific
enquiry black holes two quarks two
protons two so ever all the objects of
scientific discovery they are all
objects whatever you know in the world
is an object what we are talking about
here is unique in that it's not an
object a premiere means not
object of knowledge what is that the
pure subject of what is that not that it
is you so you are not an object don't
look for yourself in the world of
objects you are very clearly present all
the time to yourself as the ever shining
subject
it may sound poetic ever shining subject
whatever is that you should ask
hard-headed questions is the one who is
asking this question right now krishna
wants you to turn your attention into
yourself you will discover that ever
shining subject a premier not an object
of knowledge therefore you don't ask why
can't I see it why can't I hear it why
can't I smell it taste it touch it why
can't I discover it with the what the
CERN particle accelerator why can't I
discovered it with electron microscopes
no because all of them deal with objects
if it is not an object of knowledge then
how will I know it's true the question
is what is the proof that such an Optima
is there can you tell me assignment what
is the proof that what we are talking
about such a pure awareness or
consciousness is there what is the proof
yes were you winged much much much
further than but in a simple sense the
answer yes you are right of course yes
yeah life is an object it can be created
but what what is the proof that you are
pure consciousness such an you're saying
that there is an eternal unchanging
all-pervading all these things we just
said pure consciousness yes at the back
it is self-evident you might say how so
it's not evident to me buddy it will be
made evident and when it is made evident
to your reaction would be who it was
there all along you know what is the
straight answer to the question what is
the proof in Sanskrit the word for proof
is pramana the answer in a database
leontes all operation of instruments of
knowledge the objects of knowledge the
instruments of knowledge and the
knowledge generated all of them depend
on this consciousness for the efforts
for their operation serve a pramana
premiere of Viva Hara every act of
knowledge knowledge is an act you see
its it requires every instrument of
knowledge objective knowledge and the
knowledge that you gain with the
instrument and the object all of them
they are manifested enabled by this
consciousness and again if you
understand what this means you will see
it as a matter of fact of course of
course right now I am aware therefore I
see I have the X Y C means I have the
experience of seeing if you go to an
airport the door will slide open when
you come near it there's a sensor there
in a certain sense it sees you but there
is no conscious experience of seeing in
there you say how do you know Swami well
even the most ambitious designer of
those gadgets will not say that my
sensors are conscious beings they'll
never say that they are not there's no
conscious experience of saying seeing
the entire mechanism of seeing is there
there's a mechanical eye you know like a
bit like an organ and there is an object
to be seen you are approaching the door
and the knowledge is generated not as a
conscious event but practically
behaviorally it behaves as if it is
seeing you but there is no inner
experience of seeing there the inner
experience of what we call our lives
that is possible because of this
consciousness this is a so-called hard
problem of consciousness how are we
getting this experience so up remai are
very important word not an object of
knowledge if something is not an object
of knowledge what right do you have to
speak about it we have the right to
speak about it because it is evident in
every knowledge all right now let me go
ahead
so we have had we have been told by
Krishna you are not the body-mind
you're not born with the body you know
do not die with the body you are eternal
the body mind the changing and
perishable you are all-pervading you are
real and the body mind is limited and
unreal unreal means appearance dependent
reality and you are not an object of
knowledge body mind world object of
knowledge some instrument you can know
them that which knows that's what you
are so so far
now let's go ahead some very well-known
verses usually in India sometimes when
people died these the virtues the first
is a chant chant it it's it's to do it
that you are eternal you do not die so
you know why these are chanted when
people die so you can normal you'll sit
near the dead body and people are coming
to view the body which is lying in state
and there'll be somebody chanting the
the Gita we do do that in the monastery
in in India too if a senior Swami monk
passes away
when we were young novices so the world
would come to our our training center
that such-and-such swami elderly swami
is passed away the bodies kept there so
till the cremation of the body
there'll be continuous chanting of the
gita by by turn so we divide ourselves
into groups and we used to go there once
it so happened they got the advance
notice that simon Swamy has passed away
and he's there in that room the body so
you can start going start the gita
chanting and so the novices go there in
a group three or four novices with your
Geeta and they go and they see there is
a body there and it's covered with a
white cloth and the room is very quiet
so do naturally please sit down and this
opened the gate down what so they were
so dumb daivam and suddenly with a
flurry the clot is thrown aside and this
swami
irate annoyed all swami sits up and says
not me you fools the next room
I heard this story about Swami tea also
here two persons he had given
instructions that when I pass away how
you should chant the name of sri
ramakrishna jaya sri ramakrishna that
like you should chant like that once he
fainted and the gentleman who took him
to the hospital
you know they he told me the story that
I was summoned that the Swami Swami is
in critical condition so he rushed in a
car here and there was almost nobody
there so two of them there was a lady
and this gentleman this struggle because
he was heavy they struggle to bring him
downstairs put him in the car he was
lying in the backseat and they started
driving and then remembered the
instructions so I while driving they
started chanting jaya sri ramakrishna
and the swami got up in the backseat and
said not this time you fools
and then he collapsed again so these are
the verses which are chanted when people
and after death in the family or
something so here's a very famous verse
1920 hunt or be hunted on yes chain
amenity item
yes chinaman yachty Hatem moto Navi
Johnny tow a boat owner be Johnny tow
nam Huynh tina hannity nam Huynh tina
hannity he who thinks of it
that means the Atman as a slayer
remember this is the context of war so
that languages and he who thinks that it
is slain both are ignorant of the truth
it the self that means Atman neither
slaves nor is slain the famous verse
before I go into an analysis of the
verse Emerson Ralph Waldo Emerson he was
famous he was called the American plate
or the American Socrates so he has a
famous poem Brahma let me recite it to
you and see whether you can see the
similarity that's why I've got it all
right here it's a very well-known poem
Emerson if the red Slayer thinks he
slaves or if the slain think he is slain
they know not well the subtle ways I
keep and pass and turn again
I mean she's taking the that I am the
self far or forgot to me is near shadow
and sunlight are the same the vanished
gods to me appear and one to me our
shame and fame beautiful
they reckon ill who leave me out when me
they fly I am the wings
I am the doubter and the doubt and I the
him the branding sings the strong guards
pine for my abode and pine in vain the
sacred seven but thou meek lover of the
good find me and turned I back on heaven
incredible right so the first one is of
course a direct rendering of the 19th
verse of the bhagavad-gita if the red
Slayer red means in a in warlike and
fierce thinks that he is slaying and the
one who is killed thinks that I am I am
undone I am finished they know not well
the seek the subtle ways that I the self
I'm here and I I pass and I come again
that means we go through births and
deaths and then he goes on to say that
the dualities what is far forgotten by
the world to me is always present here
because I am the existence of all things
shadow and sunlight are the same to me
to the pure consciousness the vanished
guard the gods who are not you know seen
in the matter of belief the diva toss to
me they appear and one to me a shame and
fame
they reckon ill who leave me out so when
you say I am body and mind you have left
out the real nature of yourself you have
left it out you don't notice it I am and
I enable it and come to that later on I
enable everything all activities I do
not do them but because of me they are
happening I am not the doer and I'm not
the act itself but because of me all is
possible even the religion he says
either him the Brandon Singh's religion
is also I doubter and doubt I am the
doubting of the skeptic and the
believing person and the atheist both I
am it's because how I the consciousness
alone without me what doubt can there be
without me what belief can there be
strong God spine for me about the Vedic
God's Indra and varuna and Agni how do I
know this is what is meant so internet
Google is very helpful there are there
were study notes for this for him so I
read read that Indra and Verona and Agni
they cannot attain this highest reality
pure
justice is beyond them also but it is
you and pine in vain the sacred seven
the seven Rishi's they keep the greatest
of spiritual people they keep trying for
this but thou meat lover of the good so
you the humble lover of God but you find
me and then what is the result
turn thy back on heaven this is a very
interesting way to put it because moksha
is going beyond Heaven and Hell that
this continuous cycle of birth and death
going to hire locals heaven being born
here here earth are going to lower
worlds and suffering hell and coming
back again this entire cycle that's the
how the Hindus would this change see it
so he says if you attain me you turn
your back on heaven imagine in the late
19th century to say this in the East
Coast here would have been very
confusing for people
in fact Emerson gave a talk in in the
Harvard Divinity School a famous talk
where he told the Builder the graduating
class that we should regard everybody
ourself as pure consciousness as
awareness and he criticized this
overemphasis and which is given in your
studies on the person of Jesus and the
personality of Jesus you take the name
personal reality the consciousness to be
yourself and everyone ultimately is good
and everyone ultimately saved so this
this kind of teaching he very very thick
teaching video Panasonic teaching the
result was he was banned from Harvard
for 28 years when he was welcomed back
and then given the great honor of course
he was the greatest of the American
transcendentalists so in him you see the
meeting of the Upanishads an American
thought in the late 19th century before
Vivekananda came to this country Thoreau
Walden Pond he writes he used to stay
and like a hermit he writes in his
Walden he writes that every day in the
morning I read the bhagavad-gita
he says I bathe my intellect in the
stupendous philosophy of the
bhagavad-gita compared to which our
modern literature and art seem paltry
and trivial he says this is the light of
a pure dawn he's a beautiful language he
uses and I come into contact with this
when I read opened the pages of the
bhagavad-gita why am i via bringing
sorrow he was also part of the
transcendentalists his collection he had
45 books on Upanishads and Gita by a
British friend of his who sent those
books to him so that was the finest
collection of Indian philosophy in those
days on the East Coast when he died the
entire collection went to Emerson
Emerson loved reading the Gita and the
Upanishads I know so this is the poem
Bramha now if we go into the philosophy
of it what is being said here what is
said here the Atman your real nature is
not a doer Carta agent of action if you
think that you are the Slayer
you're not that means you are not the
doer of any action your consciousness
does not do anything it's not the doer
of an action it's not curta agent of
action when you do an action you get the
results experiencing the results is
often translated as enjoying the results
it may not be enjoyable and can be
miserable also experiencing the results
of one's actions in sanskrit it is
called bhakta the experiencer or ik
often translated as the enjoyer but
experienced or so we do karma kurta and
we experience the results of our Karma
bhakta that's the general idea and he
says the Atman is neither it's not a
doer not an experiencer of the results
of karma yes what is the experience it
clearly there is an experience clearly
there is a doer right now this is Swami
aren't you speaking so aren't you doing
something it is that same pure con
just as you the admin identified with
confused with I think for getting your
real nature identifying with a mind and
body
lighting up the mind and body with your
with you their weirdness giving it
existence and then you become the doer
through the mind and body and when the
experiences start coming you become the
experiencer whose experiences the Atman
didn't you just say the Atman is not the
experience the Atman in itself is not
the experience with the Atman identified
with thinking that its body mind becomes
experience then falls into the trap of
karma yes bill Gentry I am the machine
you are the driver of the machine so
instead of thinking of the Atman as I
this is Vedanta but if it's too much to
swallow in this way you can think of the
Atman as God that's a one that's that's
another way of approaching it and that's
an easier way of approaching it Vedanta
would have you think of this Appling
which is being revealed Atman literally
means the self you we are talking about
you if you really think about it it's
stupendous it might be too much to
digest but this much you can do is there
is such a thing which is in bottle which
is pure being and awareness which
transcends all doing and experiencing
and this is the god of religion that's
the beginning then what would you be the
lower self P if such a God exists within
you then that is the operator that
enables everything to happen I just
become a vessel then so Sri Ramakrishna
says that there'd in that way also you
can be free of the travails of karma
this is another person there back you
want you to ask something yes
mmm yes beginningless yes and white also
says that it's beginningless but with an
end yes that's right yeah the answer
might be God is doing this this is
natural we are born with a parenthesis
you're born with this ignorant the thing
to do is you know what they say this
question is it a natural when you come
to a certain point of hearing these
things again and again this question has
bound to come and come not just once
it's bound to come again and again you
know what the Swami's say in in in
Uttarakhand in the Himalayas they say
don't seek to establish ignorant seek to
cut down ignorant a ganker Pradesh time
at Cairo a Ganga carto what you're
asking is how did this happen so instead
of asking how did this happen clearly I
am under the influence of such a thing
how do I get out of it how did this
happen
no answer as one of the early Swami said
on this side of ignorance we had the
question and no answer on the other side
of ignorance when we are enlightened
they have the answer but no question yes
so there are a lot of discussion I think
last time also we discussed this that
there is no beginning to this and what
does it mean no beginning it's not an
caused thing which something has made
but after all ignorance is not made by
anything it's there to be cut down
knowledge removes ignorance you want to
add something to this
yes so that's a very Wittgensteinian
approach right so the Wittgensteinian
approaches you don't solve philosophical
problems you dissolve them so afterwards
it's true that notice in the lives of
enlightened people in any in Vedanta of
course but any tradition one thing you
will notice is they don't have any
question remaining over yes I am
enlightened now and the Buddha now it's
all all good except one thing why did
ignorant start at all it doesn't it
bothers that it doesn't seem to bother
them which means somehow the question is
not valid where they kind of would say
the question is not correct and we have
discussed this why the question is not
correct I mentioned it on the different
I will not go into it today it's a
convoluted discussion and just to give
you up those who have not heard this see
you are asking why ignorant now when you
ask why ignorant you are ask what are
you asking for you're asking for a cause
of ignorance whenever you ask why what
answer will satisfy you a cause why is
the grass wet because it rained or
snowed so because you need a cause why
is their ignorance you need a cause for
ignorance but the question is valid for
everything else except for ignorance why
again why because of this ignorance the
technical term is Maya space-time
causation they shall call an emitter now
if you ask why Maya this is what you're
asking basically why my I talk what
you're asking is why my am is equal to Y
space-time causation y causation
causation is cause-and-effect
whether once cause and effect is set
into motion you can ask what is the
cause of this effect what is the effect
of this cause but why what is the cause
of causation itself it's logically wrong
you can't like you can't ask what's
outside space
was outside and inside that space words
you can't ask what's before time who's
before and after a time words once time
has started you can ask before him after
one space is there you can ask inside
and outside but outside space doesn't
make sense
before time does not make sense why a
cause cause of cause does not make sense
that's why why ignorance has no answer
yes right so good karma is we define it
this way is the term for good karma in
Vedanta is Dharma the term for bad karma
is a Dharma so Dharma is variously
defined if you look at the dictionary
definition of Dharma you will find one
page of the herma it is defined as
morality - defined as religion if you're
asking what is morality then that's a
big question you asked me a question
about ethics what is good and what is
bad there are many ways of defining it
one way Swami Vivekananda zwei wall that
is selfish is evil all that is unselfish
is good interesting you can you can
problematize it all so you can you can
in but it's a very powerful insight if
you ask me whatever takes you to
enlightenment is good whatever takes you
away from enlightenment is bad sort of
operational definition if you ask a
strict believer in say a particular
religion whatever my religion commands
might take sacred texts command that is
good whatever they prohibit that is bad
now when I act in accordance with
Commandments with the do's I am doing
good when I violate the do's and would
do something that is prohibited then I'm
doing bad so this is Dharma and adharma
this generates what is called Papa and
punya merit and demerit and the result
of Punia merit is suka happiness the
Papa demerit is unhappiness so this is
basically the way the moral causality
this is called law of karma
yes sir Han Darius
let me see if I can rephrase that
are you asking what what is relative
relative to what are you saying ethics
are relative or relative to what are you
seeing are you seeing relative in the
sense that what is good for one person
might be bad for another person in that
sense part of Maya yes part of yes are
you asking what would be the purpose of
all of this how is disconnected to the
set children and the answer is it's not
really connected the answer is from
Advaita Vedanta perspective this cause
law of causation karma good and bad good
deeds bad deeds all of it is within the
movie and the sat-chit-ananda is the
screen on which the movie is playing it
is not doing good deeds or bad deeds nor
is it really affected by the not does it
enjoy the results of the good deeds nor
does it suffer the consequences of the
bad deeds but but here's the nub that
you will enjoy and suffer the
consequences of the deeds that you have
done this is enabled by satchitananda
because it gives existence to everything
it gives awareness to everything so so
from the point of advaitha from the
point of Vedanta what is what do you
have to do with all this what's what's
my perspective we've a kinda put it very
powerfully he said
good good bad bad and none escaped the
law law of karma good means Dharma good
good Dharma leads 2 ponyo leads to suka
Dharma good action leads to merit leads
to happiness
bad bad bad action adharma leads to pop
a demerit leads to unhappiness Luke and
none escaped the law he says nobody
escapes the law it's under causation
nobody means none of the jivas the the
embodied beings under in ignorance he
says whosoever wears a form must wear
the chain to who serve where's the 4
means we are all wearing forms here all
bodies he said no wears of form means
thinks that I am this one this is who I
am if you think this is who I am
then the Karma which produced this body
that will have its effect on you you
will also suffer you will also enjoy
according to the merits and demons
behind this party and whatever you do
with this body those actions also will
come upon you so far is law of karma all
this is within the movie yeah I see the
hand bit just having to be complete all
this is within the movie then what is
what is Vedanta saying what's all what
is the point here we have a Candice's
but far beyond name and form is Othman
everfree know thou art that sannyasi
bolts a ohm that's at all all this is
the movie all this is the appearance you
are the reality of the appearance if to
know that as long as you do not know
yourself as you are as long as you
identify yourself as the embodied being
as this body being born and aging and
dying as this mind which is doing good
things and bad things when you think I
am this one then the results the action
done by this is you are you are a doer
and the results will come upon you you
will be the experiencer cut a bhakta
this is exactly what the verse is saying
you are neither the real you pure being
pure consciousness and like Emerson said
they say is that they know not the
subtle ways who thinks the Slayers they
think that I'm slaying the slain things
I am slain they know not the pure
consciousness he says far beyond name
and fame mm far beyond name and farm is
Atman everfree you beyond name and form
if you would know yourself truly as you
are you are set free immediately simple
no the the screen of the movie the
screen of the movie is not part of the
plot of the movie the screen on which
the movie is playing is not a part of
the plot of the movie is not the villain
who commits a murder not the police who
comes in arrest the villain and all of
that is not the screen screen has
nothing to do with it and yet it is only
because of the screen the whole thing is
happening you as pure being an awareness
you are unaffected by anything that
happens in life you transcend it and yet
you're not these are not two different
things whatever is happening in the
panorama of life is happening because of
you you are because of your presence you
lend existence to it you lend awareness
to it bill do you remember your question
yes yes
alright you know what
there's a reason I'm smiling just a
little while ago you know you are many
of you know that tomorrow we had the
interfaith conference the moderator of
the panel is Swami at Meru pond and who
is the Swami from Houston he just came
and we got him from LaGuardia and in the
car while coming back Swami at Meru
ponder was telling me you know Bill had
a question the question was how does the
law of karma work because scientifically
there must be some connection for
causation to work so action done now in
some life how can it produce a result in
entirely different life somewhere where
is the connecting link when I thump this
table it's because my hand is in
connection with the table that the sound
is produced if there is no connection if
there is no physical causality how is
karma producing result so the Swami told
me this is the question that bill had in
the 1970s exactly the same question it's
amazing that he should ask this right
now here right yes so I don't think any
answer that I'm going to give is going
to resolve the question in so quickly
yes so that's why you can raise a
question about its scientific veracity
but consider it this way karma has three
effects according to the law of karma
three effects are produced two of which
stand the test of science what are the
two results one is an immediate result
you give food to a homeless man and the
man eats and his is fed you can see that
there's a physical result any work has a
physical result which can be easily
observed that's one effect the immediate
effect the second effect is
psychological keep sharing your food
with somebody and somebody say and you
starve to death no you get this
ecology of sharing your character
changes that also can be observed that
that it's not not it's fairly
uncontroversial keep doing an action it
becomes habitual keep doing good good
becomes habitual it's not a struggle
anymore why I said starve to death I
remembered once we were driving along
upstate New York there was a little
restaurant as we were driving past I saw
that in the remote there is nothing near
it and it said on the top says eat here
or we'll both starve I think the poor
restaurant owner you know you remember
that yes eat here or we'd both start but
it creates a habit of sharing so these
two results the physical effect and the
psychic effect both are you understand
they're the they're the
non-controversial the third one is what
is called the cosmic effect that is
where a question of belief comes in what
is the cosmic effect that some action
that I do now quite apart from the
physical effect and the psychic effect
will give me some kind of a result in
some future time in this life or the
next
that's what we primarily mean by my
Karma now there is the question bill is
asking for that Karma what is the
connecting link and it's not a question
that says is they have not thought about
they have thought about it
the purva mimamsa cos the philosophers
who are experts in the ritualistic
portion of the Vedas so the ritualistic
portion of the Vedas is all about Karma
do good and get the results and then
experience the results go to heaven or
whatever so they had elaborate fire
rituals you perform them and the result
will be an accumulation of merit and
with that accumulation of merit you go
to heaven immediately the question is
asked where is this accumulation of
merit and how it is connected to going
to heaven so they postulated something
called a drishna
a potency some kind of
factory invisible factor which carries
this result so you can see this question
is what bill is asking must have
occurred to them also why would the
other otherwise come up this with this
theory of a drifter in fact the word
adrift has entered into Indian languages
so when people say they come have bad
luck or something oh it's my odd wrist
they don't know it's a technical term
from 3,000 years ago that term fell out
of use when the theistic philosophies of
religions philosophies in India became
popular immediately you will notice
whether it's a vaishnava tradition a
Shiva tradition or shark the tradition
in whatever theistic tradition we have
in Hinduism everywhere among all the
adjectives given to God all the
qualities of God one objective is karma
deeksha the dispenser of the results of
karma or in other words answer to Bill's
question is what connects karma to its
results one answer for the believers for
those who are believed in bhakti this is
God is the connector God is thing but it
shows that they thought about these
questions and there were skeptics
materialists chair Walker's
who did not believe in God who did not
believe in this adrift or whatever so
one of the verses of the skeptics the
chair Walker's goes like this there
they're poking fun at the law of karma
of the Moomin circus they are saying if
the if the oblations offered here into
the fire
are taken by the fire fire is supposed
to be in one of the names of fire is who
tava ha one who takes your oblations to
the gods and so the gods will reward you
by taking your departed ancestor your
father to heaven that is the whole
psychology you offer these sacrifices to
the gods in the fire and the fire takes
it - it's like FedEx you know it takes
it to the gods a divine FedEx and the
gods are happy with
they will make space for your dad and in
heaven so if the offering here can take
it the fire can take it to heaven then
throw your father into the fire the it
take your father to heaven straight that
way
that's the skeptic the charvaka it's a
yes so the skepticism was there but if
you ask me which way do you come down on
I'll come down on the side of karma
ultimately we're under the denial of
karma so if there's one non dual reality
what karma who's karma where will but in
the level of transactional truth via
Baja Rica karma is there why otherwise
there is no explanation for moral
causation good leads to good this
implicit belief we have if you ask why
did this happen to me the answer from
religion would be maybe God is testing
you or the Hindu or the Buddhist would
say it is your karma what are these
answers whether it's God or karma or
whatever God is regarding a punishment
punishing the Abrahamic religions might
say that's also in a very general sense
if you look deeper inside God does not
reward and punish even in the Abrahamic
religions God does not reward and punish
erratically or whimsically God is just
because the God is just so the
punishment in reward is also just which
is another way of stating the law of
karma now what are these answers these
are answers to moral causation question
of why is it happening not the physical
part of it why did I what did this
person who is so good why did this
person get such illnesses what does
science say or the answer is because you
got infected by bacteria that what you
would say to that is oh you are telling
me how it happened I am asking why it
happened because it could have happened
to anybody
why particularly this person for that
science is no answer so this is science
would say it's an accident there is no
further you cannot push why beyond a
certain
we'll give you the physical facts this
is what happened you this person who ate
contaminated food for example and
therefore got a sickness and that's it
but why did it happen to this person not
anybody else for that there is no answer
science will say it's an accident
Laurens crossed the physicist he says if
you keep asking why it's like a child
who keeps asking why the only possible
answer is go to bed but that will not
satisfy any of us that everything is
random everything is accidental then
there is no moral purpose nothing no
meaning behind any anything happening in
the in the universe then so it leads to
a very at least straight of it to the
whole point back again I would say to
the hard problem of consciousness is
there any reality to us as conscious
beings so that's why what I would say
yes build again
true we are not using the word law in
the strict scientific sense because in a
strict scientific sense if you use Advil
the term law then the cause and effect
must both be observed and the link must
be observed and then only you can say
it's a law
how is the causation but in this case
it's the effects and causes are not
observed if you see the effects you
don't see the causes there they'll say
in your past life if you see do the
causes right now do some action you will
get the results you don't see the
results now in a future life you don't
see them together until you see the
correspondence you can't call it
strictly a law but that's true of any
moral law if you say law of honesty law
of unselfishness so somebody asked why
are you calling them laws it's not like
the law of gravity
you can't break the law of gravity if
you try to break the law of gravity by
jumping off a building we'll just die
but say if you say honesty is allowed I
can break that law see this is the
question I can break that log and tell a
lie so the beautiful answer to this I
read somewhere it says these moral laws
you actually cannot break these laws you
can only break yourself against these
laws the more you violate them the more
you're violating yourself your inner
integrity as a person you start falling
apart internally it has an effect
undoubted effect this you know this
question everything that we are right
now is it just genes and our nervous
system and our environment or is it
something beyond that so this is the
topic of the debate which we are going
to have next week is it a week after
that 28 November I hear some tickets are
still available at the Rubin Museum
Steve Mitchell he is a neuroscience and
you know scientist geneticist from
Trinity College Dublin so I guess it's
going to be a debate he is going to say
that his point is his
in the book in it which says everything
that we are is hardwired there's nothing
beyond this no consciousness or
certainly nothing that survives death no
question of any kind of soul or anything
like that it's just this body that's all
and I'm going to be talking about what
we are just talking about so we are
going to discuss this 28 and the Rubin
Museum so if you are interested mark it
in your diary and you have to register
for it evening seven-thirty I think yeah
oh no did they do I hope they do now if
you if you go to our website our website
where our society you will see a link to
the Rubin Museum page on the right hand
side you will just go there on the top
right of the page it's a home page
itself there's a link click on that
it'll take you to the place where you
have to register I think a few tickets I
spoke with the I wrote to the director
he said a few tickets are still left
let's hear the questions wait and this
gentleman first and then yes yes
me right for that you have to understand
what we are talking about here the
consciousness in which everything is
perceived including brain and nervous
system also right now it's not a
question of the enlightened person
perceiving consciousness
what is that enlightened person person
realizes that I am consciousness it does
not see consciousness as an object you
see the word which we used up Ramaiya
not an object of awareness not an object
of knowledge so the Atman the pure
consciousness is not an object of
knowledge just as we see this world just
as we experience our own thoughts they
are all objects of knowledge why because
that's how you see them when you look at
this book
you are the person seeing and the book
is an object to you are you with me when
you sink a thought Swami has a book in
his hand that's a thought that thought
is an object to you and you are the
experiencer of that thought but the
consciousness in which you are which is
lighting up all these objects that is
not an object that is what we are
discussing here self-evident it cannot
be denied it is without it nothing
else's if you deny that somebody asked
suppose you deny that there is such a
thing there's an a question in ancient
philosophy ancient Indian philosophy
they call it jagged under present the
darkness the world plunged in darkness
if you deny that awareness it's like
this if you see my hand are you there
are you seeing my hand say yes if you
close your eyes are you seeing my hand
you said no but are you there yes
are you there as an aware being you are
aware that your eyes are closed
similarly imagine that you have closed
the portals of all your senses are you
still there though you are not seeing
anything hearing anything smelling
tasting touching anything are you still
there you would say yes follow it
further if you suppress your thoughts
are you still there
instead of and if you think about it
intellectually you might say no it's
doubtful er that will be there if I have
there are no thoughts if you follow it
intuitively you will see that you're
very much there exist that you're not
thinking when your mind is blank are you
there or not when you're not perceiving
when you're not thinking feeling emoting
anything you're still there
what is that and the other question that
which is there in spite of shutting down
the senses and the mind if you remove
that and keep the senses mind and
everything what will be your experience
do you follow what will happen nothing
you are entire everything will disappear
you don't exist anymore
that one is you and the rest are apps
you can download them yes in fact the
next verse we have run out of time all
right let's just hear the questions next
words very interesting it talks about
what will happen when the apps start
failing I so as we grow older memory is
not working as well people become upset
don't be upset
you the consciousness you are aware of a
key in memory you the consciousness you
are aware of a faltering memory nothing
nothing wrong to eat with you you are
exactly the same as the body ages the
brain also ages and so certain
capacities everything slows down it's
very natural and it should not upset you
at all it's inconvenient it's
inconvenient but that's all it's nothing
wrong with you you are that same
unchanged awareness undimmed awareness
there were two other hands raised there
bilious
yes the way they have tried to establish
the law of karma is through
argumentation it's not a proof it's not
an empirical proof it's not a
mathematical proof it's more a proof
like lawyers would argue the case in
code what do lawyers do they supply a
battery of reasons evidence reasons
arguments for their case so that's how
these philosophers who support the law
of karma argue in absence of the law of
karma what other option is there
see there's this interesting book the
problem of evil in Indian philosophy
Arthur Harmon he is a professor of
philosophy in Hawaii University so you
wrote this book you know the question is
why is there evil in the world if God
exists so this is a question that every
theistic religion has to answer non
theistic religions don't have
transferred this why say Buddhists why
is there evil in the world
that's the nature of the world it's
continuously changing and that gives
rise to suffering that's it that's the
way the world is it's changes and change
gives rise to suffering but if your
religion says God exists and this God is
an all-powerful God all-knowing God and
good God loving God all powerful and not
loving you can see he will exist because
it's dictator and it may seem funny now
but the ancients thought in that way in
the pre Judaic religion there is a very
interesting story that the story of Noah
and the Great Flood so what what
happened if you look at the story in
Judaism the story is that God was angry
with humanity because they violated the
moral Commandments and so God wanted to
punish them drown them all
so God flooded the world and but he
wanted everything to
so he asked Noah who was righteous - and
then our can take animals two by two and
so on you know it's very interesting the
same story was there in the Babylonian
civilization same story but with one
crucial difference in the Babylonian
story mr. Futterman in the Mesopotamian
story there is a counterpart to Noah
there is an ark there is a flood there
is the anger of God but the difference
is this in the in the later story that
is the Jewish story God did it why
because it was just the human beings
were awful and God punished them it was
a just punishment because God is good we
were bad they are punished see justice
God did it because God is good now in
the web and the Mesopotamian story why
did God do it because the human beings
get this they were so noisy God got
disturbed and he wanted to shut them
down literally this is the story so God
did it because he could God was annoyed
because you are disturbing God not
because of any idea of good and bad so
you are in the Mesopotamian stories God
is just power like a dictator the same
story evolution of God God doesn't
evolve our conception of God evolves as
we became more civilized we said God
cannot just be a despot God must be a
good person good God so God is just when
in further evolution God is not only
just God is also loving now if you have
a loving and just God an all-powerful
God why is there evil why is there
suffering in this world if God was not
all-powerful the world is like this
because God has no other option this is
the best he could do in a very poor
designer then you can take him to
consumer Court or if God is perfect but
but not loving then you can say he has
got a designer ugly world because God
wants us to suffer but loving God which
of you as parents would not want your
children to be perfectly happy as human
beings you can't do it but suppose you
had all the power to make them happy
make their life perfect which human
parent wouldn't do it so God is our
divine parent why doesn't God made to
make life perfect
if God is existing and omnipotent and
all good and loving so this is called
the problem of evil every religion has
to answer the theistic religions in
Hinduism also have to answer in Judaism
Christianity Islam everybody answer has
to be there this is called the problem
of evil yeah no no no don't
are you going to say something about
this no oh oh hold on don't be quick to
answer I don't be quick to ask another
question
stay with this question this is
important so this is called the problem
of evil and what is the answer different
religions have come up with different
answers in Christian theology this is
called theodicy what does theodicy mean
justifying the ways of God to men
justifying the ways of God to men why
God did this so there are many theories
God is testing us you know no I don't
like that theory alright
God is making a strong and suffering
makes a strong there are many theories
like this so see what answer fits you so
what this professor Herman has done he
has collected all the answers from the
different religions of the world
different philosophies of the world even
from literature across human
civilization what is the answer to the
problem of evil and he's collected a
list of 23 answers you think there's no
answer to this question he gives you 23
answers but don't be so eager to look at
the answers none of them will satisfy
you I can guarantee you will last answer
he gives his law of karma this is the
Indians came up with this idea of the
law of karma and any examines it and he
finds the whole chapter on the flaws of
the law of karma and he says even with
this but this is by far the most it is
the most superior answer you can get the
most global it can explain many things
which other things other answers cannot
explain so he says so this is the best
that civilizations have done over the
last few thousand years and the law of
karma interestingly Hindus have many
many views within Hinduism but they all
agree on the law of karma Buddhists
don't even believe in
god this Atman that we are talking about
Buddhists have an entirely different
idea about it but they had exactly the
same idea of the law of karma the Janes
had the same idea of law of karma the
Sikhs so all the Indian civilizations
they had religions they believed in this
one senior Swami he put it this way
yeah buddy come here that way this is a
very profound principle because schools
of thought across thousands of years
with multiple philosophies multiple
theories who disagree on almost every
other point agree on this point so this
is that so we're asking what is the
justification for law of karma it's like
a battery of arguments if you read
Harmons book you will find lot of
arguments in favor of the law of karma
why it should be something like this
because the alternatives are completely
unpalatable yeah yes that is true that's
what I was just saying earlier science
can go science economics all of this can
explain something but it will only tell
you the how it will not ultimately
answer the why why ultimately this
particular baby had to suffer in a nurse
a buzz born in a famine infested area
and starve to death why you can give all
sorts of economic reasons political
reasons scientific reasons it will not
close the explanatory gap you'll still
have a moral why why this one and not
somebody else there science will tell
you that's not a question we cannot
abandon that question that's the most
vital question throws us to our hearts
this lady there yes the atman yes yes
it's not not almost like it is the who
am i question that's a yes it is a
method it's a methodology and what we
Dantas says is it's not something vague
in fact it's the most when you
understand properly what wadn't is
trying to say it's the most obvious of
things you say it can't be understood
through science but what Vedanta will
say all your science is done by that
consciousness without that consciousness
you do not see you do not hear smell
taste touch as Emerson said I am the
doubter and the doubt where is a doubt
but in your awareness where are you the
doubter but in awareness itself switch
off that that thing in the back you know
beyond the senses beyond the mind that
that awareness switch it off nothing
remains no science religion nothing
remains yes
a case for yes it cannot be directly
perceived but the method is that you
catch it whether the language they uses
it is perceived by itself it is self
revealed you know it intuitively I as I
am that and it's not in fact everything
else depends on it
you might think that's vague or that's
not how do I know that's true
in fact truth and falsity all are proved
because of its presence it's the most
once you get what they are talking about
it's the most indubitable thing in the
universe because your entire life
depends upon it so it's not proved by
the methods with ordinary methods of
knowledge by by ordinary epistemology
but what we Dante will say epistemology
depends on it
all the methods of knowledge depend on
it it's like trying to say that the
proof that these people are here is that
I see them what's the proof that you are
here I saw you so the question is the
principle is if you see it that's the
proof for its existence now if I ask
what is the proof that I've got eyes
because I can't see my eyes not directly
the way I'm seeing you if the proof for
existence is seeing and I cannot see my
eyes the conclusion would be that thing
my eyes don't exist and yet what would
the real answer be the very fact that
you are seeing anything at all is a
proof every seeing is a proof of two
things the object that you are seeing
and the eyes themselves though the eyes
themselves are not objects which you see
out there
similarly consciousness is proved by
everything in your life once you begin
to understand what we learn to say is
everything in your life points to you
the awareness and it's that conscious
operating the mind and sense organs
which stands as witness to the presence
or absence of other things
in fact as she said at the very
beginning it's a good way to end the the
existence of objects is what can be
doubted the existence of the subject
cannot be doubted it is what lights up
the doubt and you know your faith doubt
all of these come and go in
consciousness so this approach is not an
approach of faith what is an approach of
faith the guard based approach is an
approach of faith that there is such a
thing the moment you say I am that thing
you don't have to you don't need faith
to say that it's like saying that
suppose I ask you that when you come and
you sign your name and I want to know if
you came I have to look at the register
that whether you were in the class at
look at register and testifies to your
presence now if I want to know whether I
was in the class do have to look for my
name in the register was identical maybe
if it's in the long pass but right now
no because my own presence is revealed
to me directly what is that thing all
right
we'll end here and the next class is
yeah the next class is there next Friday
the next verse I want you to do it today
but we'll do it next time also with it
so it's all one of those verses which
are chanted when somebody dies Shantay
shanti shanti he hurry he own that sat
sri ramakrishna Aparna must